<!--
this file belongs to bluefish, a web development environment
Copyright (C) 2002  Denny Reeh
Copyright (C) 2005-2006 The Bluefish Project Team

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.
-->

<chapter id="debugging-bluefish">
<title>Debugging Bluefish</title>
<sect1 id="using-debugger">
<title>Using the Debugger</title>
<para>Here are the detailed steps for sending a useful backtrace to the Bluefish Developer Team.</para>
<procedure><title>Running bluefish under gdb</title>
<step>
<para>Get the latest CVS release (see <xref linkend="getting-bluefish-cvs"/> for info)</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>From <filename>bluefish-gtk2</filename>, the top directory of the bluefish source, run: <userinput>autoconf</userinput></para>
<para>You may have to set some environment variables before running <command>autoconf</command>, as well as providing autoconf with some flags. Also, some patches may need to be applied, depending on your system.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Then, run <userinput>./configure --with-debugging-output</userinput></para>
<para>Again, you may have to add some flags, depending on your system.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Once you succeed in configuring bluefish, run: <userinput>make clean</userinput> in order to remove all unnecessary files.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Then, run <userinput>make</userinput> to compile bluefish.</para>
<para>Do not run make install since it strips the debugging symbols from the executable.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Execute bluefish under gdb with: <userinput>gdb src/bluefish</userinput>. This way, you will get access to a non stripped version of bluefish, which is not the case if you run  <userinput>gdb bluefish</userinput> or <command>gdb /usr/local/bin/bluefish</command>, since those binaries do not have any debugging symbols anymore.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Once <command>gdb</command> has started, type <userinput>r</userinput> to start the debugging session.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Try to reproduce the crash in bluefish.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Copy and paste the last 50 lines of debugging output to a text file.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Type <userinput>bt</userinput> in gdb to get the backtrace, and copy it to the text file too. If the backtrace is huge, copy only the first 50 lines.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Save the text file and gzip it by running gzip textfile in a terminal.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Quit gdb with <userinput>q</userinput></para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Fill in the bug report (see <xref linkend="bluefish-filling-bug-report"/> for instructions).</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="bluefish-filling-bug-report">
<title>Filling a bug report</title>
<para>First make sure you have followed the instructions at <xref linkend="using-debugger"/> in case of bluefish crash.</para>
<para>You can use bug-buddy or go to <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/browse.cgi?product=bluefish">http://bugzilla.gnome.org/browse.cgi?product=bluefish</ulink>, the bluefish bugzilla page on bugzilla org gnome, to fill in the bug report.</para>
<para>The following instructions are related to bug-buddy. Nevertheless, though the form differs when filling a bug report from the bluefish bugzilla page, the necessary bits of information are the same.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
