<!--
this file belongs to bluefish, a web development environment
Copyright (C) 2002  Denny Reeh
Copyright (C) 2004-2006  The Bluefish Project Team

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.
-->

<chapter id="getting-bluefish">
<title>Getting Bluefish</title>
<sect1 id="getting-bluefish-versions">
<title>Choosing a Version</title>
<para>Currently, four versions of bluefish are available:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The GTK1-version (v0.7) is deprecated and no longer updated, but is the choice for those of you still running GTK1.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The latest GTK2-version (v1.0.5) is the version of choice for most users, and is regarded as stable enough for daily use.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The latest development snapshot is always one step further than the latest stable release. In it, you will find some new features, bug fixes, and a prettier GUI. The catch is that it may have	unfinished or buggy features. Try this if you want to see new features or are bothered by a bug in the latest stable release.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>CVS is the bleeding edge of Bluefish development. You may find that the CVS version has several bug fixes and enhancements, however, it may also contain new, inadvertent bugs. You will also need the CVS version if you want to contribute a patch. Although the CVS version may be unusable for short periods of time, it is often stable enough for daily use.</para>
<note><para>The CVS version comes with a compilation flag <option>--enable-unstable</option>, which allows you to install it concurrently with another version of bluefish, either the GTK2 one, or the snapshot one, or the 'normal' CVS one. It introduces supplementary functionalities. When this flag is used, bluefish is installed under the name of <application>bluefish-unstable</application>, vs. <application>bluefish</application> for any other version. This flag is enabled by default.</para></note>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>If you want the latest and greatest, read <xref linkend="getting-bluefish-cvs"/> below or  <xref linkend="getting-bluefish-snapshot"/> if you do not want to install CVS. If you simply want to use Bluefish, read <xref linkend="getting-bluefish-stable"/> for how to get the latest stable package for your system.</para>

<sect2 id="getting-bluefish-updates">
<title>How and When Updates are Released</title>
<para>Due to the small number of volunteer developers, the progression of Bluefish's development often fluctuates. For this reason, a long time may pass between each release. After all, the developers volunteer their time and effort because they actually want to <emphasis>use</emphasis> Bluefish :-)</para>
<para>Consequently the current CVS or CVS snapshots may be what you want to use. We do try to keep the CVS version usable at any time (actually, the CVS version is used by most of the development team on a daily basis).</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="getting-bluefish-os">
<title>Operating Systems Supported by Bluefish</title>
<para>Bluefish has been reported to work on a number of systems. The Bluefish team mainly support these platforms:</para>
<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem><para>Mandrake Linux</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Red Hat Linux</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Fedora Core</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Debian Linux (and derivatives)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>FreeBSD</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Actually, any GNU/Linux distribution with GTK2 is fine and many distributions include Bluefish. In fact, Bluefish will likely work quite well on any POSIX compatible OS where GTK2 is available. Bluefish has been reported to work on the following:</para>
<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem><para>NetBSD - distributed in pkgsrc</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OpenBSD - available through their ports system</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SGI IRIX - see <ulink url="http://freeware.sgi.com/"/></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mac OS X via <ulink url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/">Fink</ulink> or <ulink url="http://darwinports.opendarwin.org/DarwinPorts">Darwin Ports</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Sun Solaris</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Tru64</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>AIX</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>HP-UX</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Win32-cygwin - with a few nags.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>			
</sect2>
</sect1>

<?pagebreaka4?>
<sect1 id="getting-bluefish-stable">
<title>Latest Stable Version</title>
<para>Many Linux distributions ship a version of Bluefish or make it available through their package systems. For example, Bluefish is available through the Debian apt-system and FreeBSD's ports. You may check if Bluefish is available through your favorite software installer.</para>
<para>However, the main source is the Bluefish website, where the software and a few contributions are available. The download page is reachable at <ulink url="http://bluefish.openoffice.nl/download.html"/>. Here, you may download the source code and binary packages for Debian, Red Hat/Fedora, and Mandrake.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="getting-bluefish-snapshot">
<title>Latest Snapshot Version</title>
<para>Snapshots are made regularly to provide users with the latest functionalities without having to deal with CVS. Though often not tested, they may be convenient for evaluation. They are available at <ulink url="http://bluefish.openoffice.nl/download.html"/></para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="getting-bluefish-cvs">
<title>Latest Developmental Version</title>
<para>To get the latest version of Bluefish you will need to download the source files from our CVS repository.</para>
<para>CVS<footnote><para>Concurrent Versions System</para></footnote>, a version control system, is a widely used software development tool. It keeps track of changes to the source code, and allows for reversion to previous states. If you want to read more about CVS, have a look at the CVS-book by Karl Fogel, available at <ulink url="http://cvsbook.red-bean.com/cvsbook.html"/>.</para>
<para>The Bluefish project's CVS repository is generously hosted by SourceForge.net<footnote>
<para><ulink url="http://www.sourceforge.net"/></para>
</footnote>. For more information about them, see their site. The project 
homepage is <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/bluefish"/>. Our CVS repository contains the current Bluefish source code, including this manual. The repository is accessible by anyone, and is updated almost daily by the developers.</para>
<para>To access the repository, you need a few small utilities. They are likely to be available through your favorite source of software (ports, apt, etc). The above-mentioned CVS book is a great source for information.</para>
<para>Here's how you get the source.</para>
<procedure><title>Getting the source</title>
<step>
<para>Go to the directory in which you want to put the sources:
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> cd TheChoosenDirectory</screen></para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Log in using the command:
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> cvs -d :pserver:anonymous@bluefish.cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/bluefish \
login</screen>
<note>
<para>Hit <action>Enter</action> at the password prompt.</para>
</note></para>
</step>
<step>
<para><emphasis>Check out</emphasis> the CVS module containing the source code files:
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> cvs -z3 -d :pserver:anonymous@bluefish.cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/bluefish \
co bluefish-gtk2</screen>
A lot of files will be downloaded, and listed one by one. If you're on dial-up, this might take a bit of time. When the downloads have completed, you will find the bluefish sources in the subdirectory <literal>bluefish-gtk2</literal>.</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>Enter that directory and install bluefish using the instructions detailed in <xref linkend="installing-bluefish-devel-source"/>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</sect1>
</chapter>
