<!--
this file belongs to bluefish, a web development environment
Copyright (C) 2002  Denny Reeh
Copyright (C) 2004-2006  The Bluefish Project Team

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.
-->

<preface id="bluefish-preface">
<title>Preface</title>
<sect1 id="bluefish-about">
<title>About this Manual</title>
<para>Bluefish has a large feature set, allowing the user to customize the editing experience in numerous ways. This manual targets both novice and advanced users, providing a full resource for everyone.</para>
<para><xref linkend="part1-getting-installing"/> and <xref linkend="part2-using"/> are highly recommended for anyone new to Bluefish. They present general information, installation instructions, an introduction to the main features of Bluefish, and available shortcuts.</para>
<para><xref linkend="part3-developing"/> is oriented towards developers and testers. It explains how to debug Bluefish, contains the list of features, includes code formatting styles and a reference for all source files.</para>
<para>The manual targets the <emphasis>end user</emphasis>. To that end, we have tried to use a simple, well-explained approach whenever possible. Some typographic conventions are denoted below:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Any URLs are denoted like this: <ulink url="http://bluefish.openoffice.nl"/></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Shortcuts look like this: <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>S</keycap></keycombo></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Menu options are displayed like this: <guimenu>File</guimenu>. However, many of Bluefish's menus are quite complex. When referring to submenus, options are separated by an arrow, like: <menuchoice><shortcut><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo></shortcut><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The default keyboard shortcut is shown in parenthesis.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>When referring to user input, like issuing commands to the command prompt, a monotype font is used: <screen><prompt>$</prompt> foo -bar | bang -l</screen></para>
<note>
<para>Do not write the <literal>$</literal> character - it simply identifies the command prompt. For commands requiring root access, the prompt is shown as a <literal>#</literal>.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Finally, if you find errors or omissions in this manual, fill in a <link linkend="bluefish-contact">documentation bug report</link>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="bluefish-what-is-bf">
<title>What is Bluefish?</title>
<para>Bluefish is a powerful editor for experienced web designers and programmers based on the GTK2 GUI interface. Bluefish supports many programming and markup languages, but focuses on editing dynamic and interactive websites.</para>
<para>Bluefish is not a WYSIWYG<footnote><para>What You See Is What You Get</para>
</footnote> text editor. This is deliberate, allowing the programmer to stay in full control. To facilitate the editing process, a large number of features are at your disposal. For inserting markup and code, there are tool bars, dialogs, and predefined/user-customized menus. Syntax highlighting, advanced search/replace functionality, scalability and language function references make Bluefish a powerful tool for development.</para>
<sect2 id="bluefish-history">
<title>History of Bluefish</title>
<para>Bluefish development started under a different name. A good and free text editor targeted towards web development was not available. Olivier Sessink started the project ProSite. Chris Mazuc also started an HTML editor. On a GTK development mailing list, Olivier Sessink and Chris Mazuc saw each others postings, and decided to team up. Olivier had a basic editor, Chris had many HTML dialogs ready. After merging the code this was for a while known as the Thtml editor.</para>
<para>After a while Neil Millar joined the project to add weblint integration and a color dialog. 
Because the project became larger and more mature, a logo was wanted. After many discussions
about boring logos, Neil Millar came up with a cute blue fish. Because this logo was appreciated by all, the name changed into the final name Bluefish.</para>
<para>After this initial stage, many developers, translators, testers and users joined the project.</para>
<para>Several years have passed since the first Bluefish release. Since that time, the fish has gained a reputation as an excellent editor, with qualities like stability, usability and numerous features. Also, Bluefish is small, fast and efficient, making it usable even on slow machines.</para>
</sect2>
<?pagebreaka4?>
<sect2 id="bluefish-main-features">
<title>Main Features of Bluefish</title>
<para>This list will give you an overview of the most important or outstanding features found in Bluefish:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A What You Write Is What You Get interface</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Multiple document interface, will easily open 500+ documents (tested 3500 with documents simultaneously).</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Customizable syntax highlighting based on Perl compatible regular expressions, with subpattern support. Default patterns are included for:</para>
<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem><para>C</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>cfml</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ChangeLog</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>CSS stylesheet</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Gettext po</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>HTML</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Java</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>JScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>JavaScript</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Octave</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Pascal</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Perl</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>PHP</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Python</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>R</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Shell</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SQL</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Tcl</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Ruby</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XML</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Anti-aliased text window</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Multiple encodings support, can convert between different character sets, supports multibyte characters, Unicode, UTF8, etc.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Nice wizards for startup, tables, frames, and others</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Dialogs for many HTML tags, with all their attributes</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>HTML tool bar and tear-off menus</para>
</listitem>
 <listitem>
<para>User-customizable tool bar for quick access to often used functions</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Open files based on filename patterns and/or content, from selection or URIs</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fully featured image insert dialog</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Thumbnail creation and automatically linking of the 
thumbnail with the original image</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Multi-thumbnail generation for easy creation of photo albums
or screen shot pages</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Line numbers along the document</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Bookmarks for lines across multiple documents, with bookmark browser</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A custom menu, specify your own tags or sets of code, and define your own dialogs</para>
</listitem> 
<listitem>
<para>Custom search and replace pattern support for the Custom menu</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Very powerful search and replace, allowing POSIX and Perl Compatible regular expressions and sub-pattern replacing</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Excellent undo/redo functionality</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Configurable recent documents and recent directories functionality</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Spell checking</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Translations in <emphasis>twenty languages</emphasis></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>User customizable integration with many programs, including weblint, tidy, make, javac, etc.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>XML based function reference. Currently, references are included for Apache, DHTML, DocBook, HTML, PHP, and SQL. A GTK reference is available, and support for Perl and Python will be added. You may also create your own function reference. The XML format is described later in the manual.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>XML based reference library for CSS2, HTML, PHP, and Python.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Projects management.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>As Bluefish is a part of a larger desktop environment, we have focused on making the GUI consistent with the Gnome HIG<footnote><para>GNOME Human Interface Guidelines, accessible at <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gup/hig/"/></para></footnote>. However, we prefer not following it in every detail, as some parts are intended <emphasis>for the end user</emphasis>, while Bluefish is <emphasis>for the programmer</emphasis>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="bluefish-stability">
<title>How Stable is Bluefish?</title>
<para>Quite stable! The Bluefish developers aim to produce code that neither crashes nor leaks memory. Of course, that is not always easy to do. Leaks and crashes are often fixed in CVS as soon as they are discovered and hunted down. In addition to Bluefish's large user base, the developers use Bluefish for their daily work. So, fixing bugs and preventing crashes is always a major priority. However, some nags still exist. One example being the issue of slightly sluggish copy/paste functions.</para>
<para>For an updated list of open bugs, please go to the <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/browse.cgi?product=bluefish"/> page on bugzilla gnome.</para>
<para>We appreciate any and all contributions! Please tell us if Bluefish crashes on you :-).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="bluefish-contact">
<title>Contact Us</title>
<para>We, the Bluefish development team, welcome all comments, user requests, constructive	criticisms, and contributions. Are you curious or seeking information regarding Bluefish? Would you like to contribute by translating Bluefish or its manual? Here are your options:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><ulink url="http://bluefish.openoffice.nl/"/> - The main website where you will find news, updates, manual and more information.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><ulink url="http://bfwiki.tellefsen.net/"/> - The Bluefish WiKi is the notebook for the developers, containing a lot of information. This includes, but is not limited to: updated project road maps, status of translations.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>For bug reports and features requests, related to bluefish, its web site, and its manual, please fill the appropriate bug type at <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/browse.cgi?product=bluefish"/>, the bluefish bugzilla page on bugzilla gnome - for instructions, see <xref linkend="bluefish-filling-bug-report"/>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>You can subscribe to the users' Bluefish mailing list by sending an email containing <quote>subscribe bluefish-users</quote> to <email>bluefish-users-request@lists.ems.ru</email>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>You can subscribe to the developers' Bluefish mailing list by sending an email containing <quote>subscribe bluefish-dev</quote> to <email>bluefish-dev-request@lists.ems.ru</email>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Do you want to help translate Bluefish? Please let us know by dropping an email to Walter Echarri <email>wecharri(at)arnet.com.ar</email>, our friendly translation maintainer.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If you want to help improve the manual or write new sections, please send an email to the Bluefish manual maintainer, Michèle Garoche <email>michele.garoche(at)easyconnect.fr</email>. Guidelines for this manual can be found in <xref linkend="bluefish-manual-guide"/></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If you have a general question, drop an email to <email>bluefish(at)bluefish.openoffice.nl</email>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
 </sect1>
</preface>
