<!--
this file belongs to bluefish, a web development environment
Copyright (C) 2002  Denny Reeh

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307, USA.
-->
<chapter id="bluefish-ch-1">

  <title>general information</title>
<!--	<simplesect>    
		<para>
		</para> 
	</simplesect>-->

	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-1-sect-1">
		<title>about this manual</title>
		<para>
			Bluefish has a large feature set, allowing the user to customize the
			editing experience in different ways. This manual aim to present the novice user
			with a starting point for mastering Bluefish. The advanced user will
			find the more advanced features thoroughly documented in this manual.
		</para>
		<para>
			The manual starts off by describing how to install Bluefish, along with requirements and
			supported platforms.
		</para>
		<para>
			The next chapter, the tutorial, is highly recommended for the novice user.
			It will present a step-by-step introduction to the main features of Bluefish,
			aiming to supply a short description of the most used features.
		</para>
		<para>
			The rest of the manual contains a complete feature reference, from basic to advanced features.
		</para>
		<para>
			As a reference to the Bluefish developers and anyone interested in contributing code, the manual
			also contains guidelines for the Bluefish source.
		</para>

		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-1-sect-1.1">
			<title>conventions used in this manual</title>
			<para>
				The manual is targeted the <emphasis>end user</emphasis>. Thus, we have tried
				to use a simple, well-explained approach for the large part of the manual. Some
				typographic conventions are denoted below.
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
       		<listitem>
					Any urls are denoted like this: <systemitem class="url">http://bluefish.openoffice.nl</systemitem>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					Shortcuts you can use, look like this: <accel>Ctrl-S</accel>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					The menus in Bluefish are comprehensive, and when discussing them, you may see the <guimenu>File</guimenu>
					mentioned, and perhaps a member of it, <guimenuitem>Open Advanced</guimenuitem>.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					When you can type in something, it might be an example of the input, like this:
					<screen>$ foo -bar | bang -l</screen>
					You are not supposed to write the <literal>$</literal> character - it's simply identifying
					your command prompt. If you need to be <emphasis>root</emphasis> to execute a command,
					the prompt is shown as a <literal>#</literal>.
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-1-sect-2">
		<title>what is bluefish?</title>
		<para>
			Bluefish is a powerful editor for experienced web designers and programmers. Bluefish
			supports many programming and markup languages, but it focuses on editing dynamic and
			interactive websites. It is based on the GTK2 GUI interface.
		</para>
		<para>
			Bluefish is a WYSIWYM<footnote><para>What You See Is What You Mean</para></footnote> text editor,
			letting you, the programmer, stay in full control over the code by editing it by hand.
			To alleviate the editing process, a large number of features are at your disposal. Numerous methods for
			inserting markup and code exists, through toolbars, dialogs and predefined and user customized menus.
			Syntax highlighting, advanced search and replace functionality, scalability and language function
			references make Bluefish a powerful tool for development.
		</para>

		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-1-sect-2.1">
			<title>history of bluefish</title>
				<remark>left for someone else to write ;-) - christian</remark>
				<para>
					when bluefish said "hello world"
				</para>
				<para>
					about the development
				</para>
				<para>
					Several years has passed since the first Bluefish release. In that time, the fish has
					gained a reputation for being an excellent editor,
					with qualities like stability, usability and numerous features. Also, Bluefish is small
					and needs only GTK2 to function, making it usable even on slow machines.
				</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-1-sect-2.2">
			<title>main features of bluefish</title>
			<para>
				Bluefish has many features, this list will give you an overview of
				the most important or outstanding features.
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>A What You See Is What You Need interface</listitem>
				<listitem>Multiple document interface, will easily open 500+ documents (tested 3500 with documents simultaneously).</listitem>
				<listitem>
						Customizable syntax highlighting based on Perl compatible regular expressions,
						with subpattern support. Default patterns are included for
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>C</listitem>
						<listitem>cfml</listitem>
						<listitem>ColdFusion</listitem>
						<listitem>Gettext po</listitem>
						<listitem>HTML</listitem>
						<listitem>Java</listitem>
						<listitem>Pascal</listitem>
						<listitem>Perl</listitem>
						<listitem>PHP</listitem>
						<listitem>Python</listitem>
						<listitem>R</listitem>
						<listitem>XML</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>Anti-aliased text window</listitem>
				<listitem>Multiple encodings support, can convert between different character sets, supports multibyte characters, unicode, UTF8 etc.</listitem>
				<listitem>Nice wizards for startup, tables, frames, and others</listitem>
				<listitem>Dialogs for many HTML tags, with all their attributes</listitem>
				<listitem>HTML toolbar and tearable menus</listitem>
				<listitem>User-customizable toolbar for quick access to often used functions</listitem>
				<listitem>Open files based on filename patterns and/or content</listitem>
				<listitem>Fully featured image insert dialog</listitem>
				<listitem>Thumbnail creation and automatically linking of the thumbnail with the original image</listitem>
				<listitem>Multi thumbnail generation for easy creation of photo albums or screenshot pages</listitem>
				<listitem>Line numbers along the document</listitem>
				<listitem>A custom menu, specify your own tags or sets of code, and define your own dialogs</listitem>
				<listitem>Custom search and replace pattern support for the Custom menu</listitem>
				<listitem>Very powerful search and replace, allowing POSIX and Perl Compatible regular expressions and sub-pattern replacing</listitem>
				<listitem>Excellent undo/redo functionality</listitem>
				<listitem>Configurable recent documents and recent directories functionality</listitem>
				<listitem>Translations in <emphasis>da fr es it hu pl no ru sv</emphasis></listitem>
				<listitem>User customizable integration with many programs, including weblint, tidy, make, javac etc.</listitem>
				<listitem>XML based function reference. Currently, references are included for HTML and PHP. A GTK reference is available, and support for Perl and Python will be added. You may also create your own function reference. The XML format is described later in the manual.</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				As Bluefish is a part of a larger desktop enviroment, we've focused on making the GUI
				consistent with the Gnome HIG<footnote>
					<para>GNOME Human Interface Guidelines, accessible at
						<systemitem class="url">http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gup/hig/</systemitem>
					</para></footnote>. However, we prefer not following it in every detail,
					as some parts are noticeably <emphasis>for the end user</emphasis>, while
					Bluefish is <emphasis>for the programmer</emphasis>.
			</para>
			<para>
				Some features from v0.7 (GTK1) are not yet implemented. The main missing piece is project management,
				which will be implemented before v1.0. If you depend on this feature, v0.7 may still
				be the version of choice.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-1-sect-2.3">
			<title>how stable is bluefish?</title>
			<para>
				Quite stable! The Bluefish developers aim to produce code that neither crash nor leak memory.
				Of course, that's not always easy to do, but we do try to minimize the damage. Leaks and crashes
				are often fixed in CVS as soon as they're discovered and hunted down. The developers use
				Bluefish for their daily work, in addition to a large amount of users. Some nags do still exist,
				one problem is slightly slow copy/pasting.
			</para>
			<para>
				For an updated list of open bugs, please visit the todo-list on the Bluefish WiKi, at
				<systemitem class="url">http://bfwiki.tellefsen.net/?pagename=ToDoList</systemitem>.
			</para>
			<para>
				We appreciate any and all contributions! Please do tell us if Bluefish crashes on you :-).
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-1-sect-2.4">
			<title>contact us</title>
			<para>
				We, the Bluefish development team, always welcome all comments, user requests, constructive
				critizism and contributions. Are you curious or seek information regarding Bluefish? Do you want
				to contribute by translating Bluefish or its manual? Here's your options:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<systemitem class="url">http://bluefish.openoffice.nl/</systemitem> - The main website. Here
					you'll find news, updates and more information.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<systemitem class="url">http://bfwiki.tellefsen.net/</systemitem> - The Bluefish WiKi. Here's
					the notebook for the developers, containing a lot of information, including, but not limited to,
					updated project roadmaps, status of translations, feature requests and open bugs.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					You can subscribe to the Bluefish mailinglist by sending an email containing
					<quote>subscribe bluefish-dev</quote> to <email>bluefish-dev-request@lists.ems.ru</email>.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					Do you want to help translate Bluefish? Please do tell us. Drop an email to
					Walter Echarri <email>wecharri(at)infovia.com.ar</email>, our friendly translation maintainer.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					If you've got a generic question, you can also drop an email to
					<email>bluefish(at)bluefish.openoffice.nl</email>.
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

</chapter>

