<!--
this file belongs to bluefish, a web development environment
Copyright (C) 2002  Denny Reeh

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307, USA.
-->
<chapter id="bluefish-ch-2">

  <title>bluefish installation</title>
	<simplesect>    
		<para>
	      about different methods to have bluefish installed (distribution or own installation)
		</para>
	</simplesect>

	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-1">
		<title>requirements</title>
		<para>
			Bluefish aims to be portable, hopefully wherever GTK is ported. A comparatively small
			set of external libraries are neccessary for it to work. Any recent GNU/Linux distribution
			or other *NIX with GTK2 installed, will be sufficient. In addition to the list of requirements
			below, you may also want to look at <xref linkend="bluefish-ch-2-sect-3.5"/>. Note: These
			requirements fit the GTK2-version. If you only have GTK1, you want the last GTK1-version, v0.7.
		</para>
		<para>
			The main requirements:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>gtk v2.0</listitem>
			<listitem>glib v2.0</listitem>
			<listitem>pango 1.0</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			Optional requirements:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>libpcre3<emphasis> - for Perl Regular Expression support</emphasis></listitem>
			<listitem>libaspell<emphasis> - spell checker</emphasis></listitem>
			<listitem>grep &amp; find<emphasis> - used by the advanced open dialog</emphasis>.
						<remark>Remember to add link to the advanced open description</remark></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			Compiling Bluefish require a few additional packages. (Do remember that binary packages
			exists for many platforms. It is likely you won't need to compile ;-) ). Now, lets
			assume you want to compile, perhaps to get the latest and greatest from CVS. The requirements
			are as follows:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>Development files (header files etc) for the packages above.<emphasis>
				These are often distributed as separate packages. There is also a high probability
				you have these installed already.</emphasis></listitem>
			<listitem>gcc<emphasis> - Bluefish has been tested to compile on the 2.95 and 3.x branches.</emphasis></listitem>
			<listitem>gmake or BSD make</listitem>
			<listitem>autoconf<emphasis> - only if you are going to compile from CVS</emphasis></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-2">
		<title>quick standard installation</title>
		<para>
			There are two main methods for installing Bluefish: Compile from source or install
			a binary package. The last one is the easiest to do, so we'll cover that first here. ;-) There are
			a few different approaches, caused by the differences between systems. We'll start off by summarizing
			a few really quick and simple approaches before dealing with this problem more extensively.
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				Debian: <userinput>su - &amp;&amp; apt-get update &amp;&amp; apt-get install bluefish</userinput>
			</listitem>
			
			<listitem>
				Red Hat, Mandrake (and other Linux distributions that supports rpm):
				Download the latest .rpm from the bluefish website,
				<systemitem class="url">http://bluefish.openoffice.nl/</systemitem>
			</listitem>
			
			<listitem>
				FreeBSD, NetBSD and OpenBSD distribute Bluefish through their packaging systems.
			</listitem>
			
			<listitem>
				To compile, or install on another platform, see <xref linkend="bluefish-ch-2-sect-4" />.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-3">
		<title>general installation issues</title>
		<para>
			A few considerations before installing may be neccessary. The latest GTK1-version is v0.7, which is
			no longer updated. Unless you really want the project management feature or only have GTK1 installed,
			you should use the latest GTK2-version. A lot of bugs have been corrected, along with updates and
			new features.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want the latest and greatest, read about CVS in <xref linkend="bluefish-ch-2-sect-4"/> below.
			If you simply want to use Bluefish, get the latest stable package that fit your system.
		</para>

		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-3.1">
			<title>how to get bluefish</title>
			<para>
				Bluefish is available through several different channels. Many Linux distributions
				ship a version of Bluefish or make it available through their package systems.
				I.e., Bluefish is available through the Debian apt-system and FreeBSD's ports.
				You may check if Bluefish is available through your favourite software installer.
			</para>
			<para>
				The main source is the Bluefish website, where the software and a few contributions are available.
				The download page is reachable at
				<systemitem class="url">http://bluefish.openoffice.nl/download.html</systemitem>.
				Here, you may download the source code and binary packages for Debian, Red Hat and Mandrake.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-3.2">
			<title>operating systems supported by bluefish</title>
			<para>
				Bluefish has been reported to work on a number of systems. The Bluefish team
				mainly support these platforms:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>Mandrake Linux</listitem>
				<listitem>Red Hat Linux</listitem>
				<listitem>Debian Linux</listitem>
				<listitem>FreeBSD</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				Actually, any GNU/Linux distribution with GTK2 is fine -- many distributions also include
				Bluefish. Actually, the fish will likely work nicely on any POSIX compatible OS
				where GTK2 is available. Bluefish has been reported to work on
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>NetBSD - distributed in pkgsrc</listitem>
				<listitem>OpenBSD - available through their ports system</listitem>
				<listitem>SGI IRIX - see <systemitem class="url">http://freeware.sgi.com/</systemitem></listitem>
				<listitem>Mac OS X</listitem>
				<listitem>Sun Solaris</listitem>
				<listitem>Tru64</listitem>
				<listitem>AIX</listitem>
				<listitem>HP-UX</listitem>
				<listitem>Win32-cygwin - with a few nags.</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>			
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-3.3">
			<title>which bluefish version to use</title>
			<para>
				Currently, four versions of bluefish are available:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					The GTK1-version (v0.7) is deprecated and no longer updated, but is the choice for those
					of you still running GTK1.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					The latest GTK2-version (v0.10) is the version of choice for most users. It's the latest
					addition to the Bluefish tree, and is regarded as stable enough for daily use.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					The latest development snapshot is always one step further than the latest stable release.
					You'll find some new features, bugs fixed and a prettier gui. The catch is that it may have
					unfinished, perhaps buggy, features. Try this if you want to see new features, or if there's
					a bug in the latest stable release that bothers you.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					CVS - the bleeding edge of Bluefish development. You want this if there's a bug that bothers
					you, but is unfixed even in the latest snapshot, if you want to contribute a patch, or simply
					want the bleeding edge feature set. The CVS may be unusable for short periods of time, but
					will often be stable enough for daily use.
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				As commented in <xref linkend="bluefish-ch-2-sect-3.4"/>, the long time between stable releases
				make the CVS snapshots and current CVS an interesting choice.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-3.4">
			<title>how and when updates are released</title>
			<blockquote><para><emphasis>the development is always a deep black hole, but sometimes there is an new release :-)
				</emphasis></para>
				<para>-- Danny Reeh (Bluefish development team)</para>
			</blockquote>
			<para>A long time pass between each release. The Bluefish development is not too rapid, there's
			a small number of developers, and we occationally want to <emphasis>use</emphasis> Bluefish,
			not only develop it. :-)</para>
			<para>Because of the long periods of time between releases, the current CVS or CVS snapshots may be what
			you want to use. Bugs will be fixed and new features introduced. We do try to keep the CVS version
			usable at any time (actually, the CVS version is used by most of the development team, daily).
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-3.5">
			<title>system specific notes</title>
			<para>Different systems have different approaches to solutions and packaging. You might find
			the information below interesting.</para>
			
			<para>Mandrake:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					libpcre: Breaks pcre into 3 different pieces, make sure pcre-devel is installed if
					compiling from source. Try this command: <screen>$ rpm -ql pcre-devel</screen>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><remark>... more nags with Mandrake?</remark></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>Debian:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					If you are running <emphasis>unstable</emphasis>, you may experience unstability (ha ha)
					with Bluefish. Make sure it's not just caused by a buggy version of GTK2. If the bug is
					very obscure and strange, GTK may be the villain.
				</listitem>
				<listitem><remark>... more nags with Debian? Of course not...? -- Christian</remark></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
						
		</sect2>
		
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-4">
		<title>installing a bluefish source distribution</title>
		<para>By installing Bluefish from source, you may be able to get a newer version (CVS Snapshot, perhaps)
		than those distributed as binaries. You may also need to compile from source if there is no
		available binary for your system.</para>

		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-4.1">
			<title>quick installation overview</title>
			<para>
				This is the short installation description. Consult the other chapters if you are in doubt.
			</para>
			<para>Bluefish installed using the standard 'configure, make, make install' steps. Assuming you have
				downloaded a bluefish source package, for instance <literal>bluefish-ver.tar.gz</literal>
				(naturally, change the filename to what's appropriate),
				you complete the installation with the following steps:
			</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><userinput>tar -zxvf bluefish-ver.tar.gz</userinput></listitem>
				<listitem><userinput>cd bluefish-ver</userinput></listitem>
				<listitem><userinput>./configure</userinput></listitem>
				<listitem><userinput>make</userinput></listitem>
				<listitem><userinput>su -c 'make install'</userinput></listitem>
				<listitem>Now, type <userinput>bluefish</userinput> to run. You may delete the <literal>bluefish-ver</literal> dir.</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-4.2">
			<title>typical <literal>configure</literal> options</title>
			<para>
				The <literal>configure</literal> script is used to automatically find the appropriate settings for
				your system. Because of differences between systems, this compile-time configuration is neccessary,
				and configure solves this challenge easily -- with an added bonus of telling whether you have
				everything you need to compile.
			</para>
			<para>
				The configure-script can be configured, specifying locations of shared libraries or similar.
				This is something you most likely won't need to do, but it's easy to do if neccessary. For a
				complete list of configure options, type <screen>$ ./configure --help</screen>
			</para>
			<para>
				The Bluefish-specific configure options are
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><literal>--disable-splash-screen</literal> - simply disables the splash-screen.</listitem>
				<listitem>...</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>You might also need these:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><literal>--prefix=/usr</literal> - If you want to install in <literal>/usr</literal>. Usually, <literal>/usr/local</literal> is preferred.</listitem>
				<listitem><literal>...</literal></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>			
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-4.3">
			<title>installing from development source tree</title>
			<para>
				So, you want the bleeding edge? This guide will help you download and
				install the latest source from our CVS repository.
			</para>
			<para>
				CVS<footnote><para>Concurrent Versions System</para></footnote>, a version control system,
				is a much used software development tool. It keeps track of all changes to the sourcecode,
				who did what and why they did it. If you want to read more about CVS, have a look at the
				CVS-book by Karl Fogel, available at
				<systemitem class="url">http://cvsbook.red-bean.com/cvsbook.html</systemitem>.
			</para>
			<para>The Bluefish project's CVS is generously hosted by SourceForge.net<footnote>
				<systemitem class="url">http://sourceforge.net</systemitem></footnote>.
				For more information about them, see their site.
				The project homepage is 
				<systemitem class="url">http://sourceforge.net/projects/bluefish</systemitem>.
				Our CVS repository contains the current Bluefish sourcecode, and even this manual. The repository
				is accessible by anyone, and is updated almost daily by the developers.
			</para>
			<para>
				To access the repository, you need a few small utilities. You may have to install them. They
				are likely to be available through your favourite source of software (ports, apt etc). The above
				mentioned CVS-book is a great source for information.
			</para>
			<para>
				The first step is to cd to the directory you want to put the sources in, and then log in.
				The latter is accomplished with this command:
				<screen>$ cvs -d :pserver:anonymous@cvs.bluefish.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/bluefish login</screen>
				(just hit <action>Enter</action> at the password prompt)
				The next step is to <emphasis>check out</emphasis> the sourcecode. You can check out single
				modules, and the one you want is called <literal>bluefish-gtk2</literal>. The command is:
				<screen>$ cvs -z3 -d :pserver:anonymous@cvs.bluefish.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/bluefish co bluefish-gtk2</screen>
				A lot of files will be downloaded, and listed one by one. If you're on dialup, this might take
				a bit of time. Be patient ;-)
			</para>
			<para>
				When the download has completed, you'll find the bluefish sources in the subdir
				<literal>bluefish-gtk2</literal>. Enter that directory now: <screen>$ cd bluefish-gtk</screen>
				Next, you need to generate the configure script. That's accomplished by running
				<screen>$ autoconf</screen>
				Then, you run <literal>configure</literal> with whatever options you might want. This example will
				cause <literal>make install</literal> to install Bluefish with the specified directory
				as prefix (I.e. the binary is installed in <literal>/usr/locar/bf-cvs/bin/bluefish</literal>).
				This is most likely not what you want -- just run configure without parameters instead.
				<screen>$ ./configure --prefix=/usr/local/bf-cvs</screen>
			</para>
			<para>
				If configure fails, it'll probably give a hint telling you what's missing or wrong. Assuming it
				completed successfully, your next step is to compile this thing. Run
				<screen>$ make</screen>
				to accomplish this. When <literal>make</literal> has completed, you can install Bluefish:
				(<literal>su</literal> to root first, unless you specified a user writeable prefix to configure)
				<screen># make install</screen>			
			</para>
			<para>
				To update the sources at a later time, you run the command <userinput>cvs -z3 -q update</userinput>
				from within the <literal>bluefish-gtk2</literal> directory.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-4.4">
			<title>problems compiling?</title>
			<para>
				Can't compile? Well, your first step is to make sure you have the neccessary
				utilities and libraries. See <xref linkend="bluefish-ch-2-sect-1"/>. Next, see if your
				system is mentioned in <xref linkend="bluefish-ch-2-sect-3.5"/>. Below is list of
				well known problems that's been mentioned on the bluefish-dev list. If you're unable
				to find a solution (or if you think you have a solution others might want), feel free
				to contact us on the <emphasis>bluefish-dev</emphasis> list
				(See <xref linkend="bluefish-ch-1-sect-2.4"/>).
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<screen>make: *** No targets specified and no makefile found.  Stop.</screen>
					This will happen if <emphasis>configure</emphasis> fail and you try to run <literal>make</literal>.
					It also happens if you're running <literal>make</literal> from the wrong directory.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>... more trouble to come ;-)</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-5">
		<title>installing a binary distribution</title>
		<para>
			Different packages -- different installation. We'll cover only a few approaches here<footnote>
			<para>If you want to contribute a description on how to install Bluefish on your system, just drop us
			a note. :-)</para></footnote>, since the installation is very system-specific ;-). Lets have a look
			at some different systems:
		</para>
		<para>
			For Debian users this is very simple. To download, install and configure bluefish in
			One Swift Move, run
			<screen>$ su - &amp;&amp; apt-get update &amp;&amp; apt-get install bluefish</screen>
			You can check if the version available through apt is the latest -- see the Bluefish homepage,
			and compare the version there with what <userinput>apt-cache show bluefish</userinput> tells you.
			If there's a newer version on the Bluefish site, download it and install the package like this:
			<userinput>dpkg -i bluefish-ver.deb</userinput>
		</para>
		<para>
			For rpm based distributions, first check if your distribution
			has a recent Bluefish version. If it does not, download the rpm for your
			distribution from any of the Bluefish mirrors. Next, installing a downloaded rpm
			is as simple as pointing and clicking in your favourite gui package manager, or
			issuing the following command from the command line: (as root)
			<screen># rpm -Uvh bluefish-ver.rpm</screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			If you're using FreeBSD, NetBSD or OpenBSD, we probably won't need to tell <emphasis>you</emphasis>
			how to use your favourite package system. ;-)
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-2-sect-6">
		<title>post-installation setup</title>
		<para>
			The first time you run Bluefish it will create a directory <literal>~/.bluefish</literal>
			where all configuration is stored. This includes all preferences, customized menus,
			highlighting-patterns, file history etc.
		</para>
		<para>
			Bluefish will work right out of the box, but you can and should take advantage of the many
			customizations you are able to do. Change the font in the main textview if you don't like it,
			remove unused toolbars, add shortcuts to the customizeable menu and edit the list of
			browsers and external programs.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you are upgrading from a previous version, perhaps CVS, you should note that the syntax
			highlighting may have changed. To make sure you have the latest highlighting patterns, exit Bluefish
			and delete the <literal>highlighting</literal> file in your <literal>~/.bluefish</literal> directory.
			Next time Bluefish is started, the new defaults will be loaded. Note that this will also annihilate all
			your changes to the highlighting. A more gentle approach may be to move your current highlighting-file
			to highlighting.old, start Bluefish to get the new patterns, exit bluefish, and then run
			<userinput>diff -c highlighting.old highlighting</userinput> to find the differences..
		</para>
		<para>
			If your settings should happen to be corrupted, for some reason unusable, or you simply want to
			revert to the defaults, you may safely delete the <literal>~/.bluefish</literal> directory.
		</para>
	</sect1>

</chapter>
