<!--
this file belongs to bluefish, a web development environment
Copyright (C) 2002  Denny Reeh

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307, USA.
-->
<chapter id="bluefish-ch-4">
	<title>Learning to use Bluefish for New Users</title>
	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1">
		<title>The Menu</title>
		<para>
			The main menu for Bluefish consists of 10 options. In order from left to right these are: File, Edit, View, Tags, Dialogs, Document, Go, Bookmarks, Project, and External. All the menus in Bluefish have "tear-off" capability, meaning each window can be detached from the main Bluefish window. To accomplish this, click on the dashed line at the top of any expanded menu. A clone of that menu will then become a separate window that will remain in front of the main window. This provides easy access for commonly used menu items. 
			<figure id="main_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish Main Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/main_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>
								A screenshot of the Bluefish 0.13 main menu
							</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.1">
			<title>The File Menu</title>
			<para>
				Through the <emphasis>File</emphasis> menu a new file can be created, existing files opened, and opened files saved. Through <emphasis>File &gt; Open</emphasis> one or more files can be opened. Recently opened files (up to 15?) can be opened by selecting from the list within <emphasis>File &gt; Open recent. </emphasis>In the <emphasis>File &gt; Open Advanced</emphasis> dialog, multiple files can be opened from a directory using regular expressions. Assuming a working internet connection, files can also be opened from the web using <emphasis>File &gt; Open URL</emphasis>(make sure to type the http:// or it doesn't work...bug, maybe???). An interesting feature of Bluefish is the ability to open files by selecting the text of a currently opened file. For example, if a file has the text "/path/to/file", you can highlight that text and select <emphasis>File &gt; Open from Selection</emphasis>. The file, if it exists, will be opened in another tab within Bluefish. Finally, files can be opened via the command line by feeding filenames to Bluefish as arguments. This can even be done while Bluefish is running and the resulting file will then show up in its own tab.
			</para>
			<para>
				Paragraph about saving files
			</para>
			<para>
				Small paragraph about insert and rename
			</para>
			<para>
				Paragraph about closing and exiting Bluefish
			</para>
			<figure id="file_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish File Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/file_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>The Bluefish File Menu</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.2">
			<title>The Edit Menu</title>
			<figure id="file_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish Edit Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/edit_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>A screenshot of the Bluefish 0.13 edit menu</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
			<para>Enter info about the edit menu.</para>
			<sect3 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.1.1">
				<title>Undo/Redo Functions</title>
				<para>Info about the Undo/Redo Functions. How to set levels of undo,
				etc.</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="bluefish-ch-4-find-replace">
				<title>Find and Replace Functions</title>
				<para>
				The edit menu features several options for Find and Replace. The Find... (ctrl+F)
				and Replace... (Ctrl+H) menu items will simply start the dialogs described elsewhere in
				this manual. The Find again (Ctrl+G) item will repeat the last used search. It will 
				continue the search after the position where the previous search was stopped. If the 
				end of file is reached, it will restart at the beginning or continue with the next file, 
				depending on the search options used.
				</para>
				<para>
				The Find from selection item will search for the currently selected text. If you select
				for example the name of a function, in bluefish, or in any other program, and you choose
				find from selection Bluefish will start a new search for this selected string.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="bluefish-ch-4-shift-left-right">
				<title>Shift Right or Left</title>
				<para>
				These items will indent or unindent the currently selected text. It will normally use
				tabs for indenting, or spaces if you have 
				'indent with spaces' selected in the preferences. The number of spaces used is the same 
				as the 'tabsize' option in the preferences.
				
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.2">
			<title>The View Menu</title>
			<figure id="file_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish View Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/view_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>A screenshot of the Bluefish 0.13 view menu</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
			<para>Enter info about the view menu.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.3">
			<title>The Tags Menu</title>
			<figure id="file_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish Tags Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/tags_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>A screenshot of the Bluefish 0.13 tags menu</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
			<para>Enter info about the tags menu.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.4">
			<title>The Dialogs Menu</title>
			<figure id="file_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish Dialogs Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/dialogs_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>A screenshot of the Bluefish 0.13 dialogs menu</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
			<para>Enter info about the dialogs menu.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.5">
			<title>The Document Menu</title>
			<figure id="file_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish Document Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/document_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>A screenshot of the Bluefish 0.13 Document menu</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
			<para>Enter info about the document menu.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.6">
			<title>The Go Menu</title>
			<figure id="file_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish Go Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/go_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>A screenshot of the Bluefish 0.13 go menu</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
			<para>Enter info about the go menu.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.7">
			<title>The Bookmarks Menu</title>
			<figure id="file_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish Bookmarks Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/bookmarks_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>A screenshot of the Bluefish 0.13 bookmarks menu</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
			<para>Enter info about the bookmarks menu.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.8">
			<title>The Project Menu</title>
			<figure id="file_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish Project Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/project_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>A screenshot of the Bluefish 0.13 project menu</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
			<para>Enter info about the project menu.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-1.9">
			<title>The External Menu</title>
			<figure id="file_menu">
				<title id="figure-desc">Bluefish External Menu</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/external_menu.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>A screenshot of the Bluefish 0.13 external menu</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
			<para>Enter info about the external menu.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-2">
		<title>Changing Shortcut Keys</title>
		<para>Many menu entries are accessible via key combination; also called a
		shortcut. For example, pressing the Ctrl+S keys saves the current file to
		disk. If available, shortcut key combinations are shown on the right of
		the menu entry.</para>
		<para>What many people do not know is that they can be changed. Move the
		mouse over a menu entry, and press the key combination you would like to
		use. Immediately this combination will show up on the right of the menu
		entry. An entry can also be removed, press the backspace key when you move
		the mouse over a menu entry to remove the shortcut.</para>
		<para>To save the shortcut key combinations for later Bluefish sessions
		you can store them. In the Options menu choose Save shortcut keys. This
		will store the settings in file ~/.bluefish/menudump_2. If you want to
		restore the default combinations simply remove this file and restart
		Bluefish.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-3">
		<title>The Toolbar</title>
		<para>a little toolbox</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-4">
		<title>The File Editing Area</title>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-4.1">
			<title>Navigation trough text and documents</title>
			<para>The editing area is a standard gtk editing area. This means there are 
		many keyboard shortcuts available to navigate trought the text.</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>control+right-arrow will jump to the next word boundary</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>control+left-arrow will jump to the previous word boundary</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>end will jump to the end of line</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>home will jump to the beginning of the line</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>page-up will jump one page up</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>page-down will jump one page down</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>control+home will jump to the top of the document</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>control+end will jump to the end of the document</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>control + page-up will change to the previous document</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>control + page-down will change to the next document</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
		These shortcuts are also available when selecting text. Some examples: To select the current line, press home, hold shift and press end. To select the current word, press control+left-arrow, hold shift and press control+right-arrow.
		</para>
			<para>
		Navigating trough a large list of documents can be difficult. But if you right-click the document notebook tabs, you get a list of all opened documents.
		</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-5">
		<title>Bookmarks</title>
		<para>In Bluefish you can add bookmarks to a line in the text, and you can later use the bookmark to quickly jump to this location. Bookmarks can be temporary or permanent, the default can be configured in the preferences.
		</para>
		<para>
		Bookmarks can be added to the current cursor location by using the menu /Edit/Add bookmark, or by using the shortcut key combination control+d. You can also add bookmarks by right-clicking in the text, and selecting add bookmark.
		</para>
		<para>
		A way to add many bookmarks at the same time is using the search dialog. Check the 'Bookmark results' option, and all search results will be added to your bookmarks. For example this manual has sections, and each section is identified by a header like '&lt;sect1 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-6"&gt;'. A way to automatically get a bookmark to every section is to search for the following regular expression pattern: '&lt;sect[0-9]+ id="[^"]+"&gt;' and bookmark all results. 
		</para>
		<para>
		Bookmarks can be found in the side panel, sorted by document and line number. If you right click a bookmark, you get a popup menu with several options. Among the option is edit, which allows you to change a bookmark from temporary to permanent or the other way around, and you can name bookmarks.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-6">
		<title>Quickbar</title>
		<para>The quickbar is a user defined toolbar. All HTML toolbar buttons can
		be added to the quickbar by simply right-clicking them and selecting
		"Add to quickbar". If you want to remove items from the Quickbar,
		right-click them and select "Remove from Quickbar"</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-7">
		<title>Custom Menu</title>
		<para>here you can "bookmark" things</para>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-7.1">
			<title>What is the Custom Menu?</title>
			<para>The custom menu allows you to add "often used" strings or
			search and replace patterns to a menu. Upon install Bluefish will create
			some default entries, these will give you an idea what can be done with
			the custom menu.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-7.2">
			<title>Editing the Custom Menu</title>
			<para>changing and editing entries</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-8">
		<title>Syntax Highlighting</title>
		<para>Syntax highlighting is the coloring of words that have a special
		meaning in the language you are writing. Obviously the patterns are
		different for every language. The "&lt;title&gt;" word for
		example means "start of title" in HTML, the "function"
		word means "start of function" in PHP.</para>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-8.1">
			<title>Modifying Highlight Patterns</title>
			<para>The highlight patterns are build from perl compatible regular
			expressions. A pattern has options for coloring and style of the text it
			matches. Within a match other patterns can be used to color parts of
			that match. There are three types of patterns:
			<itemizedlist><listitem>1 Two patterns, match from the start to the end
			pattern</listitem><listitem>2 One pattern that matches from start to end</listitem><listitem>3
			Match a subpattern from the parent pattern</listitem></itemizedlist></para>
			<para>One specific pattern can also be used within several other parent
			patterns. The parent-match option is a regular expression that defines
			all parents for a certain pattern. If empty it will default to ^top$, so
			basically it will be on the top level.</para>
			<para>So how does it work? Lets take a look at a little example text, a
			piece of PHP code within some html code:</para>
			<programlisting>&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;?php
// this is a comment ?&gt;
?&gt;</programlisting>
			<para>The first thing the highlighting engine does is finding the
			pattern that has the lowest match. Using the default patterns for PHP,
			the pattern named <literal>html</literal> has a match at position 0:</para>
			<programlisting>&lt;p align="center"&gt;</programlisting>
			<para>So now the highlightiong engine searches for the lowest match in
			all subpatterns of<literal>html</literal>, in the region matched by the
			type 2 <literal>html</literal> pattern. Again, the lowest match will
			count. The pattern named <literal>html-tag</literal> has a match at
			position 1. This pattern is a type 3 pattern, so it matches a subpattern
			of the parent:</para>
			<programlisting>p</programlisting>
			<para>the match from subpattern <literal>html-tag</literal> ends at
			position 2 and it does not have any child patterns, so the highlighting
			engine continues at position 2 with all subpatterns from
			<literal>html</literal>. A type 2 pattern named <literal>html-attrib</literal>
			has the lowest match:</para>
			<programlisting>align="center"</programlisting>
			<para>This pattern does have a child pattern, again a type 3 pattern
			called <literal>html-attrib-sub2</literal> matching:</para>
			<programlisting>"center"</programlisting>
			<para>The pattern <literal>html-attrib-sub2</literal> does not have any
			child patterns, and subpatterns of <literal>html-attrib</literal> do not
			have any more matches, and also <literal>html</literal> subpatterns do
			not have any more matches. So we are back on the main level, the
			remaining code to highlight is:</para>
			<programlisting>&lt;?php
// this is a comment ?&gt;
?&gt;</programlisting>
			<para>Now a pattern named <literal>php</literal> has the lowest match.
			This is a type 0 pattern, so the highlight engine continues with all the
			remaining code, but it will not only search for the lowest match of the
			child patterns of <literal>php</literal>, but it will also use for the
			end pattern of <literal>php</literal>. The lowest match in this example
			is a pattern named <literal>php-comment-C++</literal> As you can see the
			?&gt; within the comment does not end the <literal>php</literal>
			pattern, because it lies within a subpattern of <literal>php</literal>:</para>
			<programlisting>// this is a comment ?&gt;</programlisting>
			<para>The pattern <literal>php-comment-C++</literal> does not have any
			child patterns, so the remaining code for the <literal>php</literal>
			subpatterns is:</para>
			<programlisting>?&gt;</programlisting>
			<para>It is very obvious now, the lowest match will be the end pattern
			of the <literal>php</literal> pattern, so we're back on the main
			level, and we have matched all of the code!</para>
			<para>The config file for highlighting is a colon separated array with
			the following content:</para>
			<programlisting>mode:
patternname:
case_sensitive(0-on/1-off):
start reg-ex:
end reg-ex:
start &amp; end pattern(1), only start(2), subpattern(3):
parent-match:
foreground-color:
background-color:
don't change weight(0), non-bold(1), bold(2):
don't change style(0), non-italic(1), italic(2): </programlisting>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-9">
		<title>Bluefish Preferences</title>
		<para>see in the menu Options/Preferences</para>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-9.1">
			<title>Editor Preferences</title>
			<para>editor</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-9.2">
			<title>Html Preferences</title>
			<para>html</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-9.3">
			<title>Files Preferences</title>
			<para>files</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-9.4">
			<title>User Inferface Preferences</title>
			<para>user interface</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-9.5">
			<title>Images Preferences</title>
			<para>images</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-9.6">
			<title>File Types Preferences</title>
			<para>
			Here you can define all filestypes that should be reckognised by Bluefish. 
			The defaults for these filetypes are retrieved from a file called filetypes.default 
			in ${prefix}/share/bluefish/.
			</para>
			<para>
			The filetypes consist first of a name (this name is also used in the file filters, and in 
			the highlighting patterns). Second is a list of extensions, separated by a colon (:). Third 
			are the highlighting update characters. Upon a keypress of one of these characters, the highlighting 
			engine will refresh the highlighting around the cursor. If this field is empty, any character 
			will force the highlighting engine to refresh. Special characters like the tab and the newline 
			can be entered as \t and \n, the backslash itself is entered as \\. Fifth is the icon location
			for this filetype. Sixth is whether this filetype is editable by Bluefish (whether or not Bluefish
			should try to open it after a doubleclick). Seventh is a regular expression that can be used to
			detect the filetype if a file without extension is loaded. Eight is the auto-tag-closing mode. A 
			value of 0 means that Bluefish should not close XML/HTML tags, a value of 1 means it should close 
			the tags XML style (&lt;br /&gt;), a value of 2 means HTML style.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-9.7">
			<title>Syntax Highlightning Preferences</title>
			<para>syntax highlighting, also see above</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="bluefish-ch-4-sect-9.8">
			<title>External Programs Preferences</title>
			<para>integrating external commands and browsers If you want to use for
			example a sed command as a filter, you can add it like this to the
			external commands and filters (in the preferences dialog): sed -e
			'some sed command' &gt; '%f' &lt; '%s'</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
